Well, hey, good morning, Canvas Church. Thanks so much for joining us for another week of Church Online. My name is Ryan, and I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here at Canvas, and I am so excited to just be bringing message number two of our new series through the book of Daniel. If you missed last week, I'd love to encourage you to go check that out. I'll do a quick review, and this is the second week in a row you're seeing.
And you're probably not used to that, and maybe don't even love it. But that's not Brandon's fault. He actually asked me to preach one message, and then I wrote a message that was too long. And so now we're here two weeks in a row for Daniel chapter one. So let me do a couple quick, a quick recap of last week, because we are going to build off of that a little bit this week before we hop into the rest of Daniel chapter one. We talked about in Daniel chapter one that we have an enemy that is
working behind the scenes in secular culture. And so when we look at the story of Daniel and the story of Babylon, we believe that Daniel was a real person, that Babylon was a real nation, and that the stories that we are reading actually happened. But we also believe that the nation of Babylon is kind of a shadow or a picture of how the enemy works within all secular cultures to try and get God's people to live for things that are lesser than God's kingdom. Like the enemy
creates an imitation kingdom, a secular culture where it tries to get God's people to live for things that are lesser than God's kingdom. And oftentimes, like Daniel, we find ourselves in this tug of war, this tension between living for kingdom impact and living for cultural approval. And last week, if you were here, the message might have felt a little bit pessimistic, a little bit like bad news bears.
It's meant to be one message. I wrote it together, and the first half was kind of some of the bad news, how the enemy works behind the scenes in secular culture to try and get us off track and to live for cultural approval rather than kingdom impact. And this week's kind of the good news, so we're excited about that. This week is how can we as individuals work intentionally against the enemy to have a kingdom impact in our culture.
throughout this series is that that verse we talked about last week is that we have an enemy, and we don't fight against flesh and blood, but against the powers and principalities and spiritual forces behind the culture. And so when we're talking about intentional strategies to fight against our enemy, we're not talking about the people of our culture. Like our neighbors, our coworkers, our friends who are bought into secular culture, who are bought into
postmodernism and the worldviews of this day, they are not our enemies. They are a people for us to love and to intentionally build relationships with and to point to Jesus. We have an enemy at work behind the scenes, but the people are not the enemy. I recently heard a quote this week from a pastor who said, he said, "If you don't love the world, if you truly don't love the world, then leave them alone because they've got enough problems without you."
If we don't really, truly, intentionally love the people of our culture, love the people of the world, then that's a problem. That's a heart issue that we need to address. They are not our enemies. We have an enemy, but the people are not our enemy. The people are a people for us to love and intentionally point to Jesus.
This week, we're going to look at our strategies. How can we counteract the strategies of the enemy? Just for a quick recap, we said the enemy tries to separate us from our biblical community, tries to educate us with the worldview of the day, tries to incentivize us with the pleasures of this world, and ultimately tries to get us to identify with something less than the kingdom of God.
So that's kind of where we're going to pick up from in Daniel chapter 1. If you have your Bibles, I'd love to have you turn to Daniel chapter 1. We'll be covering verses 8 through the rest of the chapter.
And while you're turning there, I want to point some things out about myself, because, you know, I have the microphone, so why not?
So, I don't know if you've noticed, and you probably haven't, and that's totally fine. I'm just a little bit offended.
But recently, I've lost a little bit of weight. I've been running a lot. Like, long distance running.
And for some of you, the type of running that I've been doing, you would say, is not long distance.
Like, you would laugh at me when I tell you how far I run, because you guys run, like, marathons and ultramarathons.
I'm not doing anything crazy like that, but I've been running a lot lately. And one of the questions I get often is,
"Why do you like running so much?" Like, people who don't like running, they're like,
"Why do you like running so much?" And my response is usually, "I really actually don't like running that much.
I just like eating tacos and not getting fat." Right?
Now, I'm joking a little bit, but any of you who have ever had any sustained long-term success
with a health plan, with a nutrition plan, you know that there are multiple approaches that you can take
so that you can still eat the food that you enjoy. You can eat good food
that isn't necessarily salads and tastes like cardboard. But if you balance that out with how much you eat
and how much you exercise, like there's some strategies that you can do so that you can still eat the food
that you enjoy and have a sustained, healthy lifestyle. That's kind of where I found myself, right, this year.
And the funny thing is, if you're anything like me, I've made this decision every January since I've ever been an adult.
Like, this year, I'm going to live healthy. This year, I'm going to lose weight. And every year, I try, and I fail, and I try and I fail.
And this year, it finally stuck. And I think the reason it finally stuck is because I found some of these strategies
that can be repeated, that are able to be sustained, that are habits that I've built into my life.
And so, as we kind of think about the message that we're hopping into in Daniel, I want us to think about it in light of that illustration, right?
Like, we know that the secular culture is trying to get us to live for the pleasures of this world.
It's trying to get us to throw in the towel on Kingdom Impact and just be conformed to the patterns of this world. Just live for lesser things.
It's kind of like unhealthy food, right? Like, we have this enemy that is enticing us to try and live for something less than what we're called to live for.
And so, we need to have some intentional strategies built into our life in order to have a Kingdom Impact, but still live in the world.
See, last week we looked at Romans chapter 12, where God commands His people not to be conformed to the patterns of this world, right?
Like He says, the secular culture is trying to get you to live for, to conform to its patterns and its worldviews.
And ultimately, the enemy wants you to conform to the patterns of this world so that you will no longer have a Kingdom Impact.
And that's a command that we should take seriously. But on the other end of the spectrum,
Daniel and the Israelites who were exiled to Babylon had a command that might seem a little bit in opposition to the command of not being conformed to the world.
It's found in Jeremiah, chapter 29. And Jeremiah in chapter 29 is writing specifically to Daniel and those who are exiled to the nation of Babylon.
And it says this, "This is what the Lord says: You will be in Babylon for 70 years." I remember we talked about that last week.
"But then I will come and do for you all the good things that I have promised and I will bring you home again."
So God says, "You're going to be in exile in 70 years, but I'm going to come and I'm going to rescue you and bring you back."
So similar to our story as believers, right? Like you're in exile in secular culture in America,
but like Jesus is going to come back one day and make everything good again. But he says, "Until then, while you're living in Babylon,"
he says, "Build homes. Plan to stay. Plant gardens and eat the food they produce. Marry and have children. Find spouses for them so that you may have many grandchildren. Multiply. Do not dwindle away."
And listen to this, "Work for the peace and the prosperity of the city where I sent you into exile. Pray to the Lord for it, for its welfare will determine your welfare."
And so on one hand, God tells us don't be conformed to the patterns of the secular world. But on the other hand, he tells us to live for the peace and prosperity of that secular world.
So there's this balance here, right, where we have to acknowledge that the enemy is at work in the secular culture trying to get us to conform to the patterns of the world.
And we're going to see from Daniel and his friends that there's a way that we can kind of live for the prosperity of a secular culture
without conforming to the patterns of the secular culture. That's kind of what we're going to unpack the rest of the morning this morning.
We're going to look at four strategies for not conforming to the patterns of the secular culture, but instead to live for the prosperity of the secular culture.
So there's this balance here, right? It's very similar to a healthy nutrition and exercise plan. Like there's this culture that we're called to live in, but not be conformed to it.
But we're called to live for the peace and prosperity of it.
So these strategies are actually going to counteract the strategies of the enemy that we talked about.
Last week we talked about the enemy's four strategies. This week we'll talk about our four strategies to counteract that.
So Daniel, chapter one, starting in verse eight, it says this, "But Daniel was determined not to defile himself by eating the food and wine given to them by the king.
He asked the chief of staff for permission not to eat these unacceptable foods.
Now God had given the chief of staff both respect and affection for Daniel.
But he responded, "I am afraid of my Lord the king who has ordered that you eat this food and wine.
If you become pale and thin compared to the other youth your age, I am afraid the king will have me beheaded."
So what we see here is Daniel is being told by the nation of Babylon to eat foods that he's not supposed to eat.
Like to break the law of God by eating these foods that he's not supposed to eat.
And Daniel, as a kingdom impact person, he's like, "I need to live in relationship to these Babylonian people.
But I also can't be conformed to the patterns of this world."
And so I have to think up until this point, Daniel has been placed in a lot of situations where he was uncomfortable with the Babylonian ideology,
the Babylonian worldview, where he was uncomfortable with the gods that they were worshiping and the situations that they found themselves in.
But up until this point, there was never a line where he felt like he was disobeying God or conforming to the patterns of this world.
Up until this point where they asked him intentionally to break God's law.
And Daniel says he's determined not to defile himself.
So what does he do? He gets angry and mad and says, "I'm being persecuted for my faith."
No, he doesn't. He asks the chief of staff for permission not to eat these unacceptable foods.
And look at verse 9. This is so important. This is going to be the key to the first strategy that we have.
It says, "Now God had given the chief of staff both respect and affection for Daniel."
So I think the first strategy that we have to counteract that strategy of the enemy, of getting us to separate from the belief system,
the family of God, is community. We are called to build a balanced community.
See, the enemy wants to separate us from biblical community.
But our response shouldn't be to gather together in small little holy huddles where we only hang out with other Christians who think like us, talk like us, act like us, believe like us.
No, Daniel did the very thing that we are called to do as we interact with secular culture.
And Daniel had a core group of believers that all throughout the book of Daniel we'll see he's intentionally in relationship with.
Right? Like Hananiah, Mishael, Azariah are Daniel's boys. Like they're tight, and all of them are committed to living for the kingdom of God, to living for kingdom impact in Babylon.
But they're not like, "Hey, let's just hang out and have a prayer meeting every single week or every single day and just ignore all of the Babylonians that are around us."
They intentionally build relationships with the Babylonians like Daniel's boss's boss. This is who he's talking to.
The chief of staff, it says, has respect and affection for Daniel. Later in chapter one, Daniel talks to just his regular boss. Same thing. Pulls him aside and says, "Hey, I have a plan for how we can still do our job.
Like we can still have successful, we can have success here in Babylon, but also so that I don't break God's law."
And so this is a strategy that we should have as followers of Jesus in a secular culture is to build a balanced community.
We should have small, intentional groups of believers in our lives that are encouraging us to stay on mission, to not be conformed to the patterns of this world,
but to still live for the prosperity of this culture and to ultimately bring kingdom values to our city for God's glory.
Throughout the book of Daniel, we see him intentionally in relationship with his buddies who are committed to the kingdom of God,
and we also see him intentionally building relationship with the Babylonians.
And one thing we can't gloss over in this, like we're so far removed from this that it'd be easy for us to be like,
"Oh yeah, easy for Daniel, but like think about the people in my life and how much different they are for me
and the beliefs that they have and the worldviews that they have and all of the things that they think about."
Like it just wouldn't work here. But we can't gloss over how much relational tension would have been between Daniel and the Babylonians.
So they literally had so many different values than Daniel would have had. They had a different diet.
They had different gods they worshiped. They had a completely and totally different worldview.
Like they could not have been more polar opposites. And yet Daniel and his friends decided to intentionally
build relationship with these people. We are called to intentionally develop relationships with our
secular neighbors, coworkers, and friends, and actually be invested in their lives and in their problems.
Invite them into our homes. Enter into their homes. Care about their problems. Worry about their struggles.
Even if their struggles, we think, are because they're buying into worldly ideologies or living for things that they shouldn't live for,
still. Realize they are not our enemies. That there is an enemy behind the culture that's trying to get them to
live for lesser things. And we intentionally love them and point them to Jesus. We build a balanced community.
And of course, like God usually does when I'm prepping for a sermon, He gave me an opportunity to put this
into practice this week. And like I normally do, I failed. Because, spoiler alert, pastors are real people
too, and we fail and we fall short all the time. So, one of the ways that I intentionally build
relationships with secular people, with people who think differently than me, have different worldviews than me, is I go to the local cigar shop.
And the reason I kind of even have to have outlets like that is, think about my life, right? Like I work at a church.
So my co-workers are Christians. And all the volunteers that I work with throughout the week
and the ministries that we're involved in, like mostly Christians. My spouse is a Christian. My family, mostly Christian.
And so it's like, I find myself, if I'm not careful, in this bubble, almost this holy huddle, where if I'm not intentional,
the only relationships I'll have are with people who follow God. And so one of these decisions I've made is to
intentionally go to the cigar shop, because it's an hour and a half, you're just sitting there with other people
having conversations, learning about their life, asking them questions about what's important to them,
the problems that they see in society and the solutions that they have for it.
And it's a great way to interact with and understand people who think differently than me.
I went in this week, and there was a guy there that I struggle with, right?
Like he's opinionated and thinks totally different than me, has a totally different worldview than I do.
And I walk in, I'm like, "Oh, he's here, man." Like, you know, I kind of just wanted to have a relaxing
afternoon and meet some new people and ended up clearing out and ended up just being me and him.
And we had a really good conversation about really deep, meaningful things.
And at the end of it, he left. And right before he left, he said, "You know, I don't go to church,
but I really like what you and Brandon are doing. And if I ever were to go to a church, I would go to yours."
He said, "But I'm not a Christian, so that's not a good idea." And like left, right?
But like in that moment, I was like, "Man, the temptation in my heart is to separate."
Because he thinks differently than me, believes differently than me, acts differently than me, has a different ideology than I do.
But in that moment, I realized he's not my enemy. Like he's the person that God's called me to love and be intentional with.
Like we have an enemy behind the scenes working to get us to live for lesser things.
But while we are here on earth, our goal is to build a balanced community.
Yes, have intentional relationships with brothers and sisters in Christ who hold you accountable.
But be intentional to invest in the lives of people who think differently than you.
Because there's going to come a day where difficulty is going to fall on them,
and you're going to have the opportunity to point them to the only one who brings hope to hopeless situations.
So we're called to build a balanced community.
The second thing, the strategy that we have, is to develop a godly character.
Daniel knew when it was time to draw the line.
Like, he knew the difference between conforming to the patterns of the world and living for the prosperity of the world.
And the only way that we can really do that, know that, is by intentionally building godly character.
And that doesn't happen overnight, right?
Like, later in the book of Daniel, we're going to see a group of people try and get Daniel in trouble.
And the thing that they use to get him in trouble is to try and make a decree so that he can't pray to God.
Why? Because they see him day in and day out going into his prayer closet.
Day in and day out working to develop godly character in his life.
And so we see Daniel intentionally strengthening his relationship with God through prayer.
And then he knows, right? Like, he knows. He's led by the Holy Spirit. He knows when to draw lines.
He knows the difference between conforming to the patterns of the world and living for the prosperity of the world.
And we, as followers of Jesus, were called to intentionally develop character that lasts, character that allows us to be faithful in the midst of struggles and trials.
Look at—I love verse—where are we at here? Verse 10.
So he's asking his boss, like, "Hey, I can't do this. Like, I want to help you.
I want to do whatever we can to figure out what we need to get done, but I really can't eat this food.
Is there any way around it?" And his boss says, "I'm afraid of my Lord, the king, who has ordered that you eat this food and wine.
If you become pale and thin compared to the other youths your age, I'm afraid the king will have me beheaded."
So, like, his boss is like, "Hey, man, I really like you. You seem like a really great guy.
You've got some cool things going on. I'd love to be your friend, and I'd love to help you out here.
But if this doesn't work, my head's going to get chopped off." Right?
And I think it's easy to—I think we could easily imply not only would his head get chopped off, but Daniel's head would get chopped off too, right?
And so Daniel has developed this godly character so that he's even willing to suffer in order to be obedient to the kingdom of God.
And I think a lot of Christians want this type of godly character, but they want it to happen overnight.
They want it to be instantaneous, right? Like, we just want to be like, "We want to have godly character that lasts right now."
And the problem is, like, that doesn't work. Like, it's the same thing if we look at the opening illustration about, like, nutrition, right?
Like, if we just do the fad diet, if we just do the one quick thing, like, yeah, we might lose a couple pounds, but at the end of the day, it's not sustainable, it's not long-term.
And so as followers of Jesus, if we're going to build godly character, we've got to find some—wow, that is a very hard word to say—sustainable practices, right?
Like, we've got to get in our prayer closet. We've got to be intentional to regularly get up and spend time with God.
To, before we go to bed, spend time with God. To find time throughout the day to spend time with God in prayer and in worship.
We've got to read the Scriptures. We've got to interact with the Holy Spirit so that we know when it's time for us to draw the line.
Like, so many times I interact with people, and they want me to tell them when they should draw the line between conforming to the patterns of this world
or living for the prosperity of the culture. And at the end of the day, like, what we want at Canvas is we want you as individuals to have the type of godly character
where you know when it's time to draw the line. You know the difference between conforming to culture and living for the prosperity of culture.
And we'll help you navigate that, but if that's going to happen long term, you've got to intentionally build godly character.
I'm going to hate on some Gen Z kids for a second, if that's okay. If you're a Gen Z in here, I love you. I'm sorry.
Everybody else, we just get a kick out of making fun of you. If it makes you feel better, the Boomers made fun of the Millennials for a long time, and now we've just agreed.
Like, we had a backroom deal where now we're just going to make fun of you for a while. In a few years, we'll invite you into the club and we'll make fun of the next generation.
Does that sound good? Cool. So, I heard about this study where eight out of ten Gen Z people believed that they would be internet famous before they died.
And we live in this culture where there's, like, instant gratification. Like, we see people become famous overnight.
People with next to no skill, people with next to no talent, like, we just see them overnight become famous.
And so we believe that there's, like, this culture about us that we could just become successful overnight.
And ultimately, godly character doesn't happen overnight. Godly character that lasts,
that's willing to suffer for the kingdom of God happens intentionally day in and day out.
Us making the decision that we're going to prioritize our relationship with Christ.
We're going to prioritize worship. We're going to prioritize accountability and community of other brothers and sisters.
So, if we want to have a kingdom impact in a secular culture, we build a balanced community.
We develop godly character. And we grow in cultural understanding.
Look in verse 17. It says, "God gave these four young men an unusual aptitude for understanding every aspect of literature and wisdom.
God gave Daniel the special ability to interpret the meanings of visions and dreams when the training period..."
So, remember, we said last week that one of the enemy's tactics is to educate people and the worldview of the day.
So, they were sent off to Babylonian College, and it says, "When that period was over, when they graduated Babylonian College,
the chief of staff brought all the young men to King Nebuchadnezzar, and the king talked to them,
and with no one was he impressed more as much as Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah.
So, they entered the royal service, and whenever the king consulted them on any matter requiring wisdom and balanced judgment,
he found them ten times more capable than any of the magicians and enchanters of his entire kingdom."
So, if we're going to have a kingdom impact in a secular culture, we've got to work hard to intentionally understand the worldview and ideology of our culture.
Like, we've got to understand their perspective. We've got to understand where they're coming from. We've got to understand why they believe what they believe,
as much as we understand why we believe what we believe. And Daniel and his friends were so good at this.
They went to Babylonian College. They studied what was going on in the culture. They understood the education
and ideology of the day. And this is not a new thing, right? Like, secular culture always has a different worldview than kingdom culture.
I think about Paul in Acts 17 in Mars Hill. He says this, "Men of Athens, I noticed that you were very religious in every way, for I was walking along and I saw your many shrines."
So we've got Paul just taking a stroll through Athens, paying attention to the culture and ideology of the day, and he realizes they're religious.
They have shrines and idols all over the place. And he sees one specific idol. He says, "And one of your altars has the inscription on it to an unknown God."
Paul says, "This God whom you worship without knowing is the one that I am telling you about."
And so Paul enters into this secular culture and looks around, tries to understand the worldview of the day, and he finds inroads in the culture to point these people to Jesus.
It's the same thing Daniel and his friends do in Babylon. Like, they intentionally understand the worldview and ideology of the day so that later in the book, we're going to find out when King Nebuchadnezzar has a dream.
Like, Daniel, through an understanding of the culture and through his relationship with God, is able to interpret what's going on and find inroads to point King Nebuchadnezzar to kingdom values.
This is what we're called to do. We're called to understand the culture that we live in. We're called to care about the culture that we live in, and we're called to use what we know about God and point the culture to what we know about God.
One way I do this, I'm a theological nerd, and you're probably going to make fun of me for this, but my wife loves the award shows, the Grammys, the Emmys, the Golden Globes, right?
Like, I don't know which ones are for what or when they're on, but Marissa loves them, and so it used to really bother me. Like, I used to get super annoyed.
She turned it on, and I'm like, this is just like a bunch of rich people getting together to complain about what's wrong with the world, and it's frustrating to me, right?
Like, I used to get annoyed, but now I've started to really enjoy it, and the reason I enjoy it is because I intentionally sit down, and I try and think through the worldview and think through the ideology of the culture of our day.
Like, these people at these award shows are cultural icons. Like, they are driving the motivating forces of our culture of our day, so the things that they say matter.
The thoughts that they think matter, and like, we need to be intentional to understand what are the driving forces behind our culture, and where does their ideology overlap with God's truth?
Because we said last week, all truth is God's truth. And so, they're going to have some ideologies that line up with ours, and we can use those as inroads to point them to the message of Jesus.
See, followers of Jesus should seek to understand the worldviews and perspectives of our secular culture, and use that understanding to look for opportunities to help our secular organizations prosper and to preach Jesus.
So, again, kingdom impact in a secular culture. We build a balanced community. We develop godly character. We grow in cultural understanding.
You've probably noticed by now that I have three C's, so you're probably waiting for the fourth C problem. Couldn't think of a fourth C, but it's a K. Close enough.
So, we grow in cultural understanding and we stay rooted in our kingdom identity. Last week we talked about how the enemy, the culture of Babylon, renamed Daniel and his friends.
They took their godly names and renamed them to Babylonian names. And what we see throughout the book of Daniel is Daniel and his friends, they let the Babylonians call them by their Babylonian names.
Like, they're okay with that. It's fine. Not a problem. You guys have a different worldview, a different ideology than us.
You can call us whatever you want to call us. But throughout the book of Daniel, Daniel and his friends never refer to themselves by their Babylonian name.
They always refer to themselves by their God-honoring, kingdom-honoring name. And not only that, sometimes, and this is funny because Daniel's writing this letter to insiders, right?
He's writing this letter to Israelites. Oftentimes, throughout the book, he actually misspells his Babylonian name.
He's like, "Yeah, whatever they call me, like, it's fine. Like, they have a different worldview. They have a different ideology than me.
They call me this, but I am Daniel. Like, I am a child of the Most High God. This is my kingdom value. This is what I live for."
So we've got to choose. No matter what the culture wants to call us, no matter what identities they want us to grab onto,
we have to choose to intentionally grab onto kingdom identities. That we are children of God.
That we've been adopted into the family of God. That we are under the lordship of Jesus. And where he tells us to go, we go.
And what he tells us to do, we do. See, the culture is regularly going to misunderstand and attempt to rename us.
But there's only so many names they can call us while we're regularly dying to ourself to love our neighbor.
Like, if we're doing our own thing, if we're just being obnoxious and gathering together in holy huddles, of course, they're going to have name after name after name after name.
But if we're following the example of Jesus laying down our life and serving our neighbors and serving the poor and seeking to demonstrate the love of Jesus in our community,
they're going to call us some names for a while, and eventually they're going to run out of names to call us.
It happens to Daniel later in the book. Like, they just wanted to hate and hate and hate on Daniel.
And finally, the king's like, "Guys, this guy is a good dude. Like, his God must be the one true God."
And so let's just be intentional to not care about the cultural identities that we're trying to get thrown into.
Let's be a people that root our identities in the kingdom of God. First and foremost, we serve King Jesus.
Let's be a people that lay down our life and remain faithful to the kingdom in the midst of a secular culture.
Verse 21, we'll wrap up here. It says, "Daniel remained in the royal service until the first year of the reign of King Cyrus."
So here's the cool thing about this. We get a spoiler alert. At chapter one, we get a spoiler alert to the end of Daniel's life.
Ultimately, what Daniel is telling us is, "Hey, I made it. Seventy years in exile in a secular culture where I was being persecuted for my faith, and I was faithful.
I had a character that lasts. I built a well-balanced community. I rooted my identity in the kingdom of God.
I understand the current cultural worldview, and in light of that, I lived for the kingdom faithfully for 70 years."
See, there was kings that changed throughout Daniel's exile in Babylon, but there was one king who remained on the throne throughout all of it.
Worldly kingdoms will change, but we have a king who sits on a throne and who is in charge of all things, and that is the king that we serve.
And if we are faithful to him, we will be able to persevere through trials and tribulations of the secular culture.
We'll be able to persevere through the changes of kingdoms on this earth, because we live for an eternal king.
I love this, because we said last week, the Bible is not just about what happened, but it's about what always happens.
And Daniel was faithful, yes, but he wasn't perfect. Daniel was just a shadow of Jesus.
Daniel was a real character, but he's also a shadow of the one who is to come.
Jesus is the greater Daniel. Daniel was faithful in a secular culture, while Jesus was perfect in a secular culture,
and ultimately was perfect on your behalf, on my behalf. The book of Daniel might give us a roadmap
to how to have a kingdom impact in a secular culture, but it also points us to the one who had the ultimate kingdom impact,
who died in our place for our sins, so that we might be brought into right relationship with God,
so that we might have an opportunity to partner with Him to have a kingdom impact in our city.
Maybe you're here, and you want to have a lifelong kingdom impact. You want to make it to the end of your life,
being faithful to the kingdom of God, having an impact in your city, but you're afraid you've disqualified yourself.
Maybe you say, "Ryan, you don't know what I've done. You don't know how I've lived. You don't understand.
I've spent most of my life conforming to the patterns of this world. How am I ever going to untangle myself from that?
How am I ever going to be intentional to point people to the kingdom when I've been living for the kingdom of America rather than the kingdom of God?"
Maybe you're here, and you say, "Ryan, I want to have a lifelong kingdom impact, but you don't understand.
I've spent most of my life separating from my community. I've spent most of my life gathered together in holy huddles, and all of my friends and co-workers are believers."
Wherever you find yourself on that spectrum, I would say it's never too late.
You're never out of the kingdom impact game. Like, Jesus has offered you forgiveness.
It's going to be the day where you can choose, "You know what? I'm going to ask forgiveness for how I've conformed to the patterns of this world, for the way that I've been living my life.
I'm going to choose today to start building a godly character that lasts. I'm going to choose today to submit myself again to Jesus as Lord and leader of my life."
Or maybe you're on the other side. You've been separating. You're going to say, "You know what? Today is the day that I'm going to choose to start loving my community,
to choose to start loving people who are far from God. I'm going to build relationships. I'm going to invest in their lives.
I'm going to do everything I can to point them to Jesus to have a kingdom impact in their life."
Maybe you're here, and you like the worldview and ideology of secular culture, and you're not really sure if Jesus is truly worth giving all that up for.
Maybe you're not sure where you're at with Jesus, and you like where you find yourself.
I'm just here to say, whether you believe it or not, we believe here at Canvas, down to our socks,
that the secular culture is the enemy's imitation of the kingdom of God.
There's things to be enjoyed in secular culture, but it just falls short over and over and over again of what God has to offer in His eternal kingdom.
So I would just plead with you, like consider the fact that you might be living for something lesser than the kingdom of God.
Don't miss out on the abundant life that Jesus has to offer because you're living for something less than the kingdom of God.
I invite you to reach out to us. Send us a message on Facebook. If you've been watching and you're considering whether or not following Jesus is worth it, we would love to talk to you about that.
So in conclusion, at Canvas, we want to be a people who work for the prosperity of the secular culture without conforming to the patterns of the secular culture.
And we do this, each one of us, as individuals. It's not going to work as a church as a whole, and it doesn't work if only a few of us do this.
All of us, as individuals, we choose to build a balanced community. We have small groups of believers that are encouraging us, challenging us, holding us accountable,
but we get into the lives of people in our culture, and we seek to have an impact. We build a balanced community.
We develop a godly character that lasts. We choose every day to invest in our relationship with Him.
We grow in our cultural understanding. We seek to understand the people around us and why they think the way that they think.
And we understand that in light of the biblical worldview, in light of what we believe to be true from God's Word.
And ultimately, we root ourselves in our kingdom identity, first and foremost. We are children of God.
We are servants of the Most High God. We serve King Jesus.
Canvas, let's be a church that intentionally seeks to live for the prosperity of the secular culture without conforming to the patterns of the secular culture.
Let's have a kingdom impact by really being invested into our community, into relationship with people who don't yet know Jesus.
And let's do everything we can to find inroads to point them to Jesus, because at Canvas, we truly believe that following Jesus is a better way to live.
Let's pray. Father, thank you for the Bible, which isn't just a story of what happened, but it's a story of what always happens.
And our heart and our prayer for Canvas Church is that we, like Daniel, would learn to be faithful in a secular culture.
That we, like Daniel, would be intentional to build relationships, to point people to Jesus, to have a kingdom impact in a secular world.
Father, give us strength and courage and wisdom to do all that we need to do. Help us to build a balanced community.
Help us develop a character that will last. Help us to root ourselves in our kingdom identity. God, help us to do the work, to understand the culture, to love people well for your glory and for our good.
And ultimately, God, we pray that as a result of each one of us as individuals doing this, that we would see, that we would see heaven come to earth.
That we would see the kingdom of God established in Winchester as it is in heaven.
It's in Jesus' name we pray. Amen.
Thank you for checking out Canvas with us this morning. We're a church of real people with real lives learning to follow Jesus.
My name is Michelle Meeks, and I am the children's pastor here at Canvas.
If you are a guest with us this morning and you would like to find out more about Canvas, you can do so by going to canvaswinchester.org/guest.
You can also download our app, check us out on social media, and find our YouTube page for more information.
If you would like to give financially to Canvas, you can do so by going to canvaswinchester.org/give.
That is all we have for you this morning. I hope you have a great rest of your day.